Yeah.
>> Where's the clicker? You got it. He's
got the question.
>> Are we Are we live?
>> I put us Yeah, we're live. Hey. Hey.
Hey, we're live.
>> Thanks for letting me know.
>> No, I Okay. Hey, what up everybody?
>> Yeah, we're live. Oh [ __ ] Okay. Uh,
hell yeah. That's f No, this is good.
Listen, this is fun.
>> We are live.
>> We are live. Uh, this is this is
actually not a problem. Uh, oh, that's
the stream for that's me puking. Sorry,
that's a different thing. Sorry. Uh, CP
Convict, I thought I said it. I That was
my bad. Uh, but you know what? It's just
is this the way it goes. So, hello
everybody. We are live. We were supposed
to be soundchecking, but I pressed the
wrong button. Uh, so we're doing this
instead. Uh, hope you're all live.
>> Yeah, we're Yeah, [ __ ] it. We're gonna
do it live. We actually are gonna do it
live. So, this is Frontier Monday. Um,
>> it's like Frontier Friday, but
objectively
Exactly.
>> Yeah, that's exactly right. It is like
Yeah. Oh my god. Uh, I'm trying to get
over to our stream so I can watch. There
we go.
>> You're doing a great job.
>> Thank you.
>> We are back. Uh, hello. I'm CCP Yoten.
This is our product or our our
development director, CCP Bowman. This
is our game director, CCP Good Fellow.
And this is that rat bastard, CCB
Overload. uh our product manager product
manager uh and we're here because uh on
the 11th we're having a patch gentlemen.
>> Has it been a long
>> air horns?
Now we should have the confetti again.
>> Uh so let's [ __ ] go.
>> I do feel bad because I did absolutely
just uh [ __ ] in uh CP convict Cheerios,
but he's a legend. He's he's he's he's
on the ball. He's getting the job done.
>> Hell yeah. He knows
>> he knows he knows button. Use the
applause button. It's a perfect
opportunity.
>> It's one of those over there.
>> It's one of those buttons.
>> Press it all.
>> No.
>> Okay. So, we we do this uh before every
big cycle uh because we we want to get,
you know, not only be transparent about
what we've been doing, but also build a
little bit of hype. So, today we're
going to go through the patch notes. We
have patch notes for cycle or it's going
to be patch 0.5.1
is the start of cycle 5 which is called
the shroud of fear. Uh which is a pretty
cool name. We have new art coming out as
well if you want a new background for
your computer.
>> It's a very appropriate title as well
having been played.
>> Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Anybody who was on
that
>> It's almost like we planned this [ __ ]
>> Yeah. Right. Anybody who was on the
grid, anybody who was on the grid on uh
on Sunday knows exactly how much fear
there is to be shrouded. Uh we if you
were not part of this chat,
>> especially by NPG,
>> listen,
>> as all those that follow,
>> we persisted for a long time on that.
>> Uh I think we only lost a couple ships
and including my own. But uh yeah, we we
fought Zodi Tisa on Sunday that was kind
of nuts. He was very big and scary and
mean and he had a lot of bad little men
follow him around. And boy, how do those
bad little men just [ __ ] me up. So,
>> yep. You're welcome, by the way, cuz I
was there uh just keeping things smooth.
You didn't notice it, but I was healing
you.
>> Yeah, I saw you heal my each my uh my
whole hit points at one point. I did
want you the one who teleported me
outside of uh the Zerod model as well.
>> You're asking if I took you from your
position of cowardice and let you face
the enemy head on the position I was
taking inside the model of Zordism.
Apparently, uh there's some subtrauge
going on there. Okay. Um but all this
being said, uh cycle 4 is about to wrap
up. Uh it's been a hell of a cycle. We
had a bunch of big stuff come out in
December. Uh it's been a long time since
we've done a big cycle release. This was
our longest cycle so far at 3 months,
but cycle 5 is very nearly here. Yep.
So,
>> I know uh probably only the brightest of
minds in the community were able to
crack the code that we had a stream on
Friday and said a release is imminent.
So, I know we're catching most people
off guard. Probably like most people
only like the brightest of
>> it. It definitely didn't help that we
didn't immediately send out an email
that said, "Hey, by the way, the cycle
starts on on Wednesday."
>> We did do that. Yes. Okay.
>> Uh I don't know if it was intentional.
Shout out to CCP.
I don't know his name. GCP name um the
young lad
>> Omega.
>> Omega. That's right. I do know his name.
I don't
>> So, I know all of our colleagues names
because I respect them as people like
you.
>> We're going to look away from that. So,
we're going to go through the patch
notes. Uh you're going to see everything
or just about everything that's going to
be in here. We have some videos. We have
some images. Uh I I specifically
included not every single thing that
you're going to see visually because I
want people to be able to go out there
and actually see it for themselves
because I can tell you right now, at
least visually, visually,
>> my god, it is nuts. insane.
>> So,
>> and it's also a snapshot of what is
coming on uh Wednesday.
>> Yeah,
>> there's immediately a patch the day
after which we've been working hard on
>> and then uh this is the the delta
between um mid mid early January to now.
This is everything we've been able to
do. Momentum is increasing. So, they're
going to see more and more during this
cycle as well.
>> For for all the
presumably thousands upon thousands of
uh fans of uh project management
tracking tools,
>> uh I had a look at how many Jira tickets
are attached to the release for
Wednesday. As of this morning, it's over
>> and each of those each of those is like
a full thing. There's more. We checked
as well more than 30,000 change like
file changes and stuff in this release
versus uh just a couple of weeks ago.
like an air migration thing,
>> right? That's not that
purely features biggest technical lift
we've done for a new cycle. And actually
to c to come on to that briefly,
normally as you know, dear dear
founders, uh when we do these uh cycle
resets, it's quite uh quite a big thing
to reset everything, deploy the new
stuff. So we usually go down around 11
uh UTC, aim to come back up.
>> We're going to talk about this at the
very end of the stream,
>> are we? FYI, I have a slide for that.
>> Okay. Well, I'll just Never mind then.
>> Okay. It's It's a good slide. I promise.
Forearming. Might take us longer.
>> It might take a little bit longer than
the than the hour it usually does.
>> Um there are a couple things just to get
out ahead of it a little bit. There are
a couple things that didn't make it in
for this patch. I know uh destruction
and rebuilding uh didn't quite make it
in, but
>> this is one of the things we talked
about a little bit earlier. We're
committing to a pretty big patch, not
the day one patch, but not too long
after that where I think we're going to
see a lot more little things get in
here. Oh yeah, it won't it won't wait
until we get to another major milestone.
It was these are things that we promised
we'll deliver them.
>> And that's the nature of development.
Yeah. We are extremely transparent with
our intent.
>> Uh we overachieve in some places, we
underachieve in others and then we keep
everybody up to date on what the hell is
going on.
>> Speaking of overachieving, uh unrelated
if you haven't seen it yet viewers, uh
great trailer went out today featuring
your you over here.
>> I have to watch it.
>> USC Maximum Cats. Maximum Cat's looking
very ethereal in that uh in that trailer
with the long flowing locks.
>> Proper chat.
>> Yeah, real real proper chat energy.
Okay, enough enough faffing about. Let's
go to the patch.
>> Let's see the good stuff.
>> Like chat or something.
>> Yeah, here's a very exciting Yeah,
right. Here's the very exciting uh new
uh key art. Love that for us. Looks very
cool. Uh all right, so let's take it
through. So this is the slide we show
basically every time we do one of these.
Yes.
>> Uh this is still of course what we are
aiming for. We want to continue to be
grounded in science. We want the world
to feel real. We want it to feel
predictable,
>> intuitive, immersive,
>> built on rules that make logical sense
so that you can reason with it. Whether
it's flying
>> the story of the game,
>> everything should feel intuitive. The
best way for something to be intuitive
is it if it's encranted in science.
>> Real.
>> Yeah.
>> Uh we want it to be a cruel survival
experience as well. We want it to feel
unforgiving, something you have to
conquer, something you have to overcome.
uh there is no reward but through
adversity. Uh certainly that is why of
course war is the greatest uh greatest
endeavor. It is the the ultimate
adversity unlike peace. Um and then of
course obviously we want to be
rebuilding a broken war. We want give
players the tools
>> to to create civilization out of the the
ether. Basically we don't want them to
just be handed the gift of civilization.
We want them to have to work for it
>> um
>> and define it. We want them to decide
what their civilization will look like.
>> Yes.
>> And build the world with us as well.
>> Motors. It's a very meta meta pillar
>> indeed. Okay. So, we continue. Uh this
is uh again just sort of our our golden
path is what we're aiming for. We're in
here somewhere uh in terms of what kind
of of experience we're now able to put
through. But more exciting than that,
here's the timeline we we released a
couple weeks ago. And hey, look, here we
are. We're over here towards the end of
this this section. Uh we we've been from
founder access now we've done five cycle
or this four cycles coming into the
fifth cycle. I've helped I've added this
helpful infographic here. See where you
are.
>> Good.
>> Yeah. Uh pretty useful. Um
>> I had one critique. I would put the
arrow on the other side of the line.
>> So because we're not quite there yet.
>> We're starting. We got two more days.
>> You know what? It's a good point. It's a
good point. Uh okay. So let's get into
it then. So here's the first big news.
>> Yep. want to get this ahead of
everything because this is the the
biggest technical lift we've had to do
so far at least
>> except maybe the Python upgrades.
>> The Python upgrades,
>> but this is this is
>> equivable. Yes,
>> excuse me.
>> I think that's a word.
>> Equivocable.
>> I think equivable is also
>> I don't know if equivalent
equivalent.
>> It can be equivalable.
>> It is equivable.
>> We are moving to the sweet chain. Uh if
you don't know what that means, there's
a whole uh dev blog about it. You can
check out all the details. Uh, no words
in the chat. Understand how big of a
deal this is. Uh, and know that this is
a
>> shout out to the team for for who've
accomplished this is going on Wednesday
because it is
>> a huge lift. They've had to be working
uh to almost to to do something that you
shouldn't even notice.
>> Yes.
>> H they've spent months and months and
months building something that you would
literally go it feels the same.
>> That's the point.
>> Yeah. Be the same but smoother. Shout
out to the sweet team as well. Uh we
have true partners there that are
extremely passionate about Frontier
being a success and now that the
technical like
a lot of effort has gone into the
technical migration which is as as O is
talking about uh it should just work
smoothly if intended. But now after this
we can put all this brain power that
went into the
>> the lift into making cool stuff for
builders, cool stuff for uh players
playing the game to make the game itself
better much faster like allowing you to
do different things and be good. This
may come as a surprise to everyone on
the stream. Uh um as brilliant of a man
that CB Good is
>> humble as well.
>> He is not the best engineer in the
world.
>> Oh,
>> I know this is a shocker. Uh but this is
a revealing moment here.
>> However, uh CB Goodfella is stubborn
from the north of Iceland.
>> Yes,
>> that's true.
>> It's a tough place to live.
>> Yes. and uh CB has been uh
being the patient zero. Okay.
>> On build the documentation be close to
the mic.
>> Uh been experimenting building role
playing as a third party developer. Um,
and if I switch to first person speaking
now, I've had an awesome time, um, and a
surprisingly easy time building third
party applications on this new tax
stack. And I am not a good engineer. Uh,
I just like creating cool stuff and I am
stubborn and I I am fine with exposing
how little I know on on on some things.
So if you're out there, if you're
passionate about creating cool stuff,
agnostic of how good you are as an
engineer, uh try out the the hackathon,
build that stuff.
>> $80,000 US prize pool. If you're just
hearing with us for the first time,
check it out.
>> Big old and I mean that from the bottom
of my heart. This is a super cool work
that the team has done and it's much
more testament of their ability of
creating something that is easy and
understandable rather than uh my own
ability. And as we as we say here, you
know, if Good Fellow's capable of doing
it, anybody is really. So,
>> yeah,
>> if he can get out of bed in the morning,
so can I.
>> Exactly. Exactly.
>> Really interesting, too. Uh, and this is
a big deal for just I mean, obviously
the the the the chain swap is kind of a
big deal for developers. Obviously, most
players probably aren't going to aren't
going to recognize too much of a
difference with this. They're not really
going to see the the
>> Yeah, that's the beauty of it. Not at
first.
>> Not at first. But uh where this is going
to make a big deal is for uh location
obuscation which comes out of the door
immediately
>> because we've had issues with the past.
>> I think probably understandably issues
with the past where players were able to
very easily find basically anyone else
in the universe as long as they put
structures down because
>> all the structures all the structures
were available and easily seen on grid.
So now we're getting rid of that. You
can only see the structures as a hash.
You no longer see the exact location in
the universe. Uh we are of course aiming
for down the road making some of that
information something that you can then
give to other people. We are I was just
working with CCP on that before
>> uh we are working on having that in a
point release as early as possible.
Basically, if you want to reveal the the
location, broadcast it. If you think
about it that way, you can do it.
>> Like if you're running a network of like
fuel depots or something like that, you
want people to be able to know where the
nearest uh overload's finest fuel is and
head over there. basically you the
person the builder that created this
assembly.
>> I choose if I want to
>> reveal it
>> reveal the the coordinates of
>> so if you wanted to reveal the location
of your local gas station you certainly
could do that and let people know hey
here's a a place where you can come and
be safe in my the warm you know embrace
of my uh facilities my war machine. uh
but you don't have to and you certainly
may not want to in some cases uh
certainly I think has been the case for
a lot of players that they would have
rather well not known where all the
network nodes are
>> and and then you pair that with with not
proper defenses uh on thing no recovery
it has been uh Frontier has been rough
>> it's been rough it's been a rough part
of town
>> uh okay so this is like I said a big
deal there's only one slide about it but
I cannot understate how big of a deal
this is
>> shout out to our team, the Eveet team.
Shout out to the Missing Labs team.
>> Uh overseated. Yes. Thank you. Uh it's a
big deal.
>> Yeah.
>> Uh okay, moving right along. Let's get
into the sauce. So, here's the first big
deal. This is signature and scanning. Um
so, we are introducing a new way to find
things in a on a grid in an area
directly around you. What you're seeing
here is what's called the pass the first
iteration of this is the passive
observation system. And what that means
is instead of just saying, okay, you do
or you don't see something nearby, now
you have what are these these unverified
signatures, right? Things in space
around you. Your ship natively is going
to constantly try to resolve what it
sees as unknown signatures around it at
range. Okay? If something is right up on
top of you, you'll be able to see it
like normal. But if something is, you
know, 100 km away, 200 km away, your
ship is not going to know what it is
immediately.
And you're going to have to try and
resolve what that signature is. If that
means that you, you know, have to, you
know, perform some action, you have to
get closer to it. You have to spend more
time looking at it. Any number of things
to to to see what this thing is, that
then changes. Like I said, we I think we
we take this away from, you know, it's
no longer just you see it or you don't.
There's now this gradient of
understanding. And the way this works is
by, you know, introducing signatures. So
the first signature that we're
introducing are the gravitational
signatures. And that basically just how
much gravity, how much mass does the
thing have, right? So your ship, and
you're going to see this here in a
second. You can actually see this little
icon here in the bottom right. This is a
the first of these. This is what these
signatures look like in space. Over
there on the right, you can see the
gravity signature trying to resolve. Uh
that bar there indicates how much mass
the thing has. And you can see the the
the white bar and the orange bar tried
to convene in the middle or at some
point in in between the two of them and
that will be you know sort of the the
resolved signature. Um we actually have
a video uh if I want to go to the I'm
sure you guys will get screenshots of
this. You can post them at whatever you
need to do. It's it's not a big deal.
You understand this. Um,
>> so the cool thing about this one, as I
can say quickly, is yeah,
>> uh, first of all, there's a bit of like
just basic uncertainty because now
there's signatures that maybe only like
50 km away from you and it hasn't
resolved yet and you're sort of twling
towards it and you're like, is this
loot? Is this an NPC? Is this a baddie?
And then it pops in, you're like, oh,
it's an NPC. Yeah.
>> Oh no, it's a big one. Then they because
it's based on mass. If you're in like a
very small ship,
>> the time you resolve a much bigger
signature, let's say another player in a
bigger ship,
>> you're going to resolve them before
they're going to resolve you. So you
know they're there and you can turn
around and they might not know you're
there yet. So there's now an advantage
for having like light scouts to go ahead
because they're going to be harder to
detect by enemies or you keep your heavy
uh forces like in reserve because you
bring in the heavy ships, they're going
to be detected much further out.
>> So that becomes a really cool bit of
counterplay. This is all available for
the hackathon as well, right? This will
be in the system. So, I know there was a
question that
>> Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. And I think it's
important to note here this paired with
other things as well.
>> Pacing of the game, especially related
to progression or kind of how fast you
can go through different systems or make
decisions etc is being changed. Yeah. Uh
you need to find out more things about
the world.
uh there will be some players I am sure
of I'm just kind of predicting that feel
like they suddenly they are they are
progressing way slower than before and
then they will get worried because they
are not progressing as quickly as they
used to be. Frontier is is harsh when it
comes to competition and fenting of
other people's attacks etc. Just know
that this impacts everybody equally.
Everybody's game is about to drastically
change as you need to
>> find out what is in the world of This is
a system that we can build on over time.
So as you mentioned, this is the first
one, gravitational signatures. There's a
couple of examples here like EM and heat
signatures. So for example, two light
ships that are identical in every way
would detect each other at the moment at
the same range. But in the future, maybe
one of them is like running a bunch of
mining lasers at the same time. So
they're generating a lot of heat. So
they're going to be much more detectable
on the thermal things further out. So it
allows us to really expand on this and
add way more ways of detecting people,
being detected, hunting people, and
being hunted. I've seen CCP Paragon uh
not that long ago talk about some like a
communication signature as well where if
a if a group of ships are in a fleet,
>> they might put out like transponder
signatures that you pick up on uh where
you can like if you you see a fleet
nearby, you can all of a sudden see a
bunch of signatures all talking to each
other,
>> which is very spooky.
>> So that's not in this build to be very
clear, but now we have the technology
that allows us to do this.
>> Uh I have a video here actually that'll
show you a little bit of how this works.
So here's the first instance of it. You
can see if you look over here off there
in the distance, there's this little
icon. And we're going to zoom in on it.
And you're going to see when you zoom
in, this thing just kind of jitters
around. It's your ship trying to resolve
whatever this thing is. It doesn't know
what it is. It might be a player. It
might be an NPC. It might just be a
rock. Uh, and honestly, depending on the
player, it might be a player and a rock.
Um,
>> but it's a mid mass.
>> But it is a mid mass. You can see over
there on the right how it's how it's
trying to resolve. you know, it's not
huge. Certainly not huge.
>> Um, but you know, as you get closer to
this thing, you can you you will
eventually resolve it into something
that your ship can then read. Um, in
fact, I have another video right after
this showing in a little bit more
detail. So, here we are in another uh
orbital zone, and we'll get to orbital
zones here in a little bit. And over
here, we can see a signature that is
getting close to being resolved. We're
getting a lot closer to it. And I think
it it resolves itself when we go into
tactical mode. Here it does. And there
it is. Now you can see it. It is an
asteroid. But what you're going to see
here, it's kind of cool, and we we we I
skimmed over this just a minute ago. Um,
but we're going to see it in this video,
too, is this. While you are constantly
trying to resolve these signatures and
get more information about them. The
same is true about losing information if
you look away. Correct. Or if you put
yourself in a position where you can no
longer see it. And you're about to see
here in just a moment.
>> There's a signature that's going to show
up here. or two signatures is going to
show up just over here down there. But
because I've now gone behind this rock,
they both disappear. I can no longer see
them.
>> Signal's being blocked.
>> The signal has been blocked. So if I
want to see if I want to be able to
resolve that signature, I now need to
come around this rock. And you'll see
them start to pop back into your ship is
actively trying to resolve whatever it
it it thinks is over there.
Watch this.
All right. Now we have a line of sight
with it again. All right. There it is
trying to resolve it and then it's going
to flicker away because we're really
really far away and it doesn't have any
information about it. Uh though it is
trying to you can see it it it it's it
quick. Oh yeah, see it's losing
information pretty fast. So you it is a
a gradient a pretty wide gradient
>> pops in of uh yeah
>> and if you see that flickering it's it's
at the extreme range that you're picking
it up. So that tells you information
right there. What is kind of interesting
about this, and I I think I mentioned
this to to uh somebody fairly recently,
is this idea that you can be sitting
somewhere in space and you'll have a
signature suddenly appear somewhere in
the distance and you don't know if that
signature is just an NPC passing by or
just a rock that maybe you've gotten
close to or another player and that
other player doesn't know this might not
know the same thing about you,
>> but they might.
>> But they might and you have no way of
knowing.
>> They might have known it a lot longer
than you knew.
>> Correct. I I think it's worth calling
out. Maybe you have it. Uh what is not
in this release but is we're working on
in terms of the active active.
>> Oh yeah, we don't have that in here. Uh
but yeah, that's uh we have I think we
had a prototype announced or
one of
>> the meetings, didn't we?
>> The team is extremely greedy about
getting it in as soon as possible
because they're so passionate now about
scanning a signature overall. So one
thing is this passive, which is kind of
the detectors that you have on your ship
that detect things that are around you.
The other thing is then if you actively
want to find out more about your
surroundings obviously knowing
signatures that comes at a at a cost as
well in terms of you know uh
>> your own signature.
>> Yes. Exactly. Uh Casper in chat wanted
to know can this create phantom
signatures like signatures that aren't
actually anything.
>> Not in this build.
>> No. But what's very interesting is that
it can create uh you can basically
disappear as your signature by being
near something else that is a big
signature. We also talked about things
like like you know in World War II for
example they used to use like submarines
would pop out these like fizzing
canisters that would make a lot of noise
in the water uh for the hydrophones to
lock onto for the ships. We talked about
having like deployables and uh like
decoy drones like you launch a decoy
thing that generates like a lot of like
signal noise and kind of maybe disrupts
a long range signature scan on you while
you can try and escape and things. So
that gives us a lot of opportunity to
add in these things,
>> but we built the technology and the
infrastructure for it now exists. So
it's now data and data is a lot faster
than the infrastructure.
>> This is systemic. This is a very
important systemic leap.
>> Yeah. And to be very fair to this has
not been balanced. Not not really. Uh so
there there's probably a lot of tuning
work that needs to go into it.
>> But I can tell you right now just from,
you know, playing through it over the
last
>> already fun.
>> It's so much fun. In fact, it was so
weird the other day when we were doing
the the Moon Eater thing or the Moon
thing, the Zero thing because when you
go to the Zerod in um the newest build,
the build that we've got in the test
server, when the enforcers all spawn in,
they spawn in as unconfirmed signatures.
And what's really scary about is that
when you get unconfirmed signatures that
spawn in space around you, there's this
little like ticking sound when a new
signature pops in. Just like a
>> Yeah, just like a little popping sound
of like
>> a geer current.
>> It's exactly what it is. It's like this
little like weird little tick
>> danger uh saying like, "Hey, there's a
new signature nearby." And all of a
sudden you're sitting here then they're
like tick tick tick tick.
>> Yeah. I can imagine you're just sitting
like mining like you hear the sort of
like hum of the mining lasers and you
hear like a tick and then tick tick
tick. You're like, "Oh, what's happening
here?" And I saw a fleet coming in.
>> Yeah. Yeah.
>> Are we not going to tell the community
about the skill signature thing?
>> The what now?
>> So, we had a we were experimenting with
uh the skill signature thing where it
like picks up on your your skill as
well.
>> I see what's going on here. Uh was was
playing and it just always came out zero
and we're still trying to debug what
that means.
>> Fascinating. Somebody
>> was in the patch notes.
>> No, I know. No, it was you
>> known defect.
>> Yeah, it's a it's a known defect. We are
trying to debug it. We have our best
minds of
>> you talk a lot for somebody who could
wear like a hat. Um okay,
scooting on ahead. Uh let's talk
character progression. So you already
saw a little bit of this in cycle four,
but this is getting wildly expanded in
cycle five. Uh we now have shell
industry, shell fittings and crowns. Uh
so writers are now able to take to
manufacture their the shells they create
which are the bodies that your yourself
inhabits. Uh lets you um then control
you can control the production of those
shells, the storage of those shells and
the enhancement of those shells. We've
introduced now two new structures to
industry. That being the nest and the
nursery. The nursery is how you
manufacture shells. Uh you can you can
use them to build shells over time. And
the nest is where you put the shells
once you've uh you've manufactured them.
Over here on the right, you can see a a
an example of what the um the nursery
looks like. Uh at least the industry
page for the nursery. You have the
aggressive shell, the reaping shell, and
the rugged shell. These are just the
first three manufacturable shells um
that you can uh you can get out. Uh
these are obviously pretty to be clear,
you don't have to do this. You can still
use just a basic shell if you want to,
but if you want to get the most out of
your experience, your your your um
memories just allows for more must
freedom of choice for players.
>> And it's awesome. uh uh the the people
that have been with us for longer will
know that um
in December we introduced the first
version of C progression and we talked
about going from zero to one is the big
win and now as we have that in it is way
easier to build on top of that getting
this in now sky is the limit for more
complexities in industry that opens up
mastery it opens up kind of
specialization
>> shell trading
>> yes exactly
>> do we intentionally name a shell after
the [ __ ] reapers. We We do have a
reaping shell. There's no way we did
that on purpose.
>> I as envoy of peaceful trade empire.
>> Yeah. Okay. All right. Yeah. Yeah. Sure.
Sure. Okay.
>> For my great.
>> Okay.
>> The nest is a small scale storage
facility. This is what you use to house
your shells. Once they're produced, uh
you can store them in there. Uh it acts
just like a normal storage unit, but
specifically for bodies for for for
shells. Um, we also have now a shell
sheet, which is what you do. You go into
to improve those shells. You can equip
them with crowns. You use the memories
to make crowns. Um, and then you can use
those crowns to uh, you know, customize
and improve the shells. We have a little
bit of footage here of interacting with
the shell industry. Going to pull us
back back here on screen. This acts just
like a normal industry system. Uh, you
have ingredients you have to put into it
to actually build the shells here. uh
and then it will uh print one out. Uh
they do take a little while and this one
takes I think 10 hours to produce. Um
but they are worth having. They they
have at least straight out of the gate
some pretty significant benefits. Um and
then over here you can see me
interacting with uh so this is the
standard incarnation shell that I'm
wearing right now. If I then go over
here to the nest and open up, you can
see thick boy, my rugged shell. I have
activated it. Uh now you can see my old
incarnation shell go into the nest as a
result. And now I open it back up and
here we are. A thick boy. This is This
is my This is my new rugged shell. Now,
in this video, I didn't have
>> level zero much like you.
>> Well, indeed. In this video, I didn't
have any memory, so I I couldn't really
do anything else with it. But take my
word for it. If you have memory, you can
do some cool improvements here. Uh and
we'll have more information about that,
uh, you know, coming out before too
long.
>> This is like the visuals also of it. And
this is where we are taking the
experience overall. uh the characters
in Frontier to serve to be shown more to
players and used more by players etc. We
have an extremely talented character
team on on Frontier
>> and uh now we are starting to see more
the light of day when it comes being
able to show what characters are clones
>> indeed
>> the self in Frontier.
>> Yeah. Uh all right let's keep going. So,
this is just more information about this
uh about the character sheet itself.
We've now overhauled the character
sheet. It has all this information in
it. Um we've also updated the ascension
protocol UI. So, when you go to ascend
and you go to turn those memories into
something that you then can turn into,
you know, improvements for your shell or
for yourself rather, um that is uh that
has all been smoothed out. At least it's
been updated. Um still a lot of updates
to come with it as well. Yeah. I mean,
basically with the with the crowns, the
ability to to store your memory into a
crown and then use those crowns to
>> pass on those tra.
>> Right. And is it the way for you to to
to take your experience, your your
learned experience day-to-day on in the
frontier and turn that into uh something
that is is a can be an advantage,
>> persistent item.
>> Yeah. Exactly.
>> Yeah.
>> Um
>> which can be lost.
>> Can be lost. Yes. Here's one that I'm
very excited about. Uh camera
improvements. There have been a lot of
them. Shout out to our uh crack uh art
intern, CCP uh Manbjorn, who's been
working on knowing a lot of these.
>> Thick boy intern.
>> Our thick boy intern, CCP Manjorn, uh
who I'm sure loves this every time it
Betty thinks it's funny every single
time. Um we've introduced a couple
different cameras, uh uh two new
cameras, one improved cameras, then a
couple different camera alterations. Uh
we're going to go through these each
individually here in just a moment. So
just kind of look at this real fast.
Look at it. Look at it. Look at it.
Okay, going ahead. So, we have the chase
camera. This is something we've kind of
alluded to in the past in some of the
videos we've put out. The chase camera
is, and you're going to see it here in
just a minute, too, a camera that kind
of just swings uh on a on a hotkey back
behind your ship uh and will sit there
until you tell it to move. Otherwise, um
the orbit camera is just a standard
camera where you can drag it and move it
all over the screen. But the chase
camera, you just hit the C button and it
will immediately take the camera and
just park it back behind you. Um great
for maneuvering in tight spaces. I can
do that for goddamn sure.
>> I have used it significantly for that
reason. Also, it's very cinematic.
>> Um,
>> we also now have a tracking camera. Uh,
if you select a target and hit T, your
camera will then focus both on you and
the target that you're now tracking,
>> being able to put them both in the same
frame all the time. Super useful if
you're trying to track, you know.
>> It's super cool. All of it.
>> Yeah, it's very, very nice. Um, we also
have a a new composition manager that
just kind of makes things more visually
interesting on screen. Tries to keep
things lined up in a way that is uh
engaging. Um, and like I said, we'll
you're going to see um here's what the
chase camera looks like. So, you're just
flying along, zooming along. You press
the C button here in just a moment. And
there we go. Now, we're locked in behind
it. And it just sort of softly follows
you. It's not like the previous track
because I know people were able to like
track my own ship before. Um, and that
would lock the camera hard behind the
ship. This is a little bit softer.
You'll see some more softer turns in
here, too. Um, I'm glad I used this
video because the video before this I
got a little bit greedy and went to
between two rocks and absolutely got
myself stuck. This is
>> No, you just went nowhere between
>> I didn't even aim close didn't even aim
close to one. I wanted to avoid it
entirely,
>> but but this is if I can add some color.
Yeah, please.
>> It was a super good threat on Reddit. I
was just dunking on our controls.
>> Yes.
>> Um uh which is good. Uh like we are
creating a a game that is visceral,
focuses a lot on momentto moment
gameplay where you are skillfully
navigating your spaceship in in close
encounters. You really feel like a
spaceship captain in a in a way. Uh
there's a lot
it's very easy to say that
>> uh there's a lot of vizardry from a
cracked thick boy manion
intern and others as well to make that
feel good. This is a step in that
direction. It feels way better already
but we are nowhere near done with uh
that as well. But uh saying HD controls
is uh one thing. Doing it making it good
uh is a whole another because people who
have been playing FPS games or whatever
have have a very kind of specific
assumptions on what that means when it
comes to fidelity of of of control of
the characters.
>> Yeah. And we have some specific um
assumptions right now built into this.
And as we go forward, I can give those
to the players so that they can define
that experience more themselves.
>> Yeah. And you can see in here too, this
is what the tracking camera looks like.
It'll always try and put the the target
in the center of the screen and keep
your ship in there as well. Um, which is
super super useful. Uh, let's go back to
this next one, I think. Yep, here we go.
We've also updated the telescope mode.
The telescope camera previously was kind
of [ __ ] uh and just kind of like was
super jittery in and out. It was not a
very smooth experience. It has been
improved pretty significantly. I can
tell you I'm actually using it now for
the first time ever. Uh, and you can see
it a little bit here. Um, for example, I
want to I want to look at this bad boy
up over here. I can do that without the
the camera just jumping all over the
place. Yeah,
>> it feels much smoother. And of course,
I'm not seeing a whole lot here because
there's some smoke.
>> But I can look over here. Oh yeah, look
at that.
>> And we are working on the sensitivity
still on like because it's a different
grades of zoom in and then the
sensitivity kicks in. So there are some
adjustments there that we will need to
continue to do. But also then giving
freedom to players to be able to think
about like a scope of of a gun to be
able to depending on your preference of
sensitivity to be able to
>> configure it.
>> You can actually see the the targeting
reticule for the the future manual
firing mode moving around the screen
there whenever you move the uh the
cursor around.
>> That is an upcoming feature. We have not
included that one in this uh but I think
we talked about it on the road map
stream not too long ago. Yep.
>> Manual firing is coming.
>> Yes. sooner rather than later.
>> Manual targeting basically targeting the
ability to to
>> to shoot at an to interact at a
distance. Yes.
>> Is what it is. It's not just shooting
projectiles. It is any interaction at a
distance.
>> Uh so this is super cool. I love that
one. Shout out to that team for working
on these. I that chase camera is so
cool. Uh and is going to make for a lot
of really cool uh footage certainly. Uh
and really makes it feel like you are
playing with a chase camera with the
hand on the stick and mouse. Oh, I love
it. It's so good. Uh there's also a new
undock camera. This is not super flashy
or anything. Um and it's not a a a huge
like a massive improvement, but is
smoother. It's a little bit more casual,
a little more cinematic. This is not a
great one because it's not pointing at
the sun.
>> Good job.
>> Yeah, great footage. Listen, I was up I
was I've been up since 3:00 a.m.
>> I showed you the other day how to calm
down.
>> I showed you the other day how to turn
>> I was doing this an hour before I left
to come into the office. Sir, I'm very
tired. You need to give me a break. I
literally showed them how to turn the
sun around for cinematic.
>> Show me how to turn the sun around. All
right, we're going to go ahead and skip
this. This
>> This is great. This is fantastic.
>> Super good.
>> I didn't see any you smart ass.
>> You have a really good monitor. It looks
wonderful.
>> It does look great in my on my OLED. Uh
so we have some base building updates as
well. By the way,
>> I like how you picked the one with the
old asset.
>> Well, yeah, of course. And this is in
the game right now. Yeah, but there's
there's other ones that have new assets
that look but play the game. Then you'll
see that
>> we have you have to like you move
position.
>> Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Okay. All right.
All right.
Need a moment here. Let me myself. Um so
we've now introduced construction sites.
We talked about these not that long ago
uh with the base building team uh about
how we're now going to be implementing
um something that is not quite uh tribal
base building but is in the same
ballpark and we're getting very close.
So instead now of of just building and
we're going to have a video of this here
in a moment too. Instead of now just
building directly from the build menu,
you can put down the these construction
sites. You move over to the construction
site. you deposit the the the
resources for that site from
>> not just your ship,
>> but from any storage container in the
area. Uh so you don't have to have all
the stuff in your ship. If you want to
build something, you can just build it
straight out of a storage unit. Uh and
that will deploy it into space like
this. Anybody, any player, any player
period, can deposit material into these
sto construction sites to build them
out. Um, and since since it is um a
little bit more time intensive because
you do have to like put the thing down,
then go over there and deposit the stuff
into it, we have reduced the
construction times by 20% for all
structures uh to make it just a little
bit easier. Yep.
>> Um, which is super super nice. Uh,
outside of uh your your base, if you're
just out in the field, not putting down
any portable structures or we're now
calling field structures, um, still
requires you to have the the material in
your cargo hold, but when you're at your
base, you can kind of, you know,
freewheel it. Wesley asks um what about
SSUs? Can you take from them too? The
answer to that is no. We are still uh
well we'll get to that essentially
because we've been just moving
everything over onto SWU. So this is
feature par. So you should expect for
the most part interactions with things
like the SSUs and stuff to be as it was
or as it is today on stillness. Um but
that's like kind of on our list of
things to do once we are running forward
with.
>> Yeah. Yep. Okay. Uh we now also have
here we go. Here's a cool video. So, you
can see there are a couple structures
put down here. Uh, first of all, I love
the new build mode grid. It's super hot.
Uh, this is not super new, but it is
cool. Uh, so what you do then is you put
down a structure. In this case, we're
going to put down a turret. Uh, we're
going to drag the turret up over here.
And then you're going to press F, and
that will just put down a construction
site. Uh, the construction site is not
building currently. It is just a a thing
in space that says, "Hey, you can
deposit material here."
>> Yeah. Um, and then we'll you'll see it
here in just a moment, too. Um,
we're going to actually I think do one
more here. Uh, yes, we're going to do
one more. Yeah, here we go. So, we'll uh
then Yeah, one more down. Listen.
>> Um,
>> beautiful. All right. With that down,
then you just interact with it and then
you have this new interface. The new
interface allows you to drop material
into it. And then once you've dropped
the material in, it will begin building.
Um, and that's what you're seeing here.
There is a new build animation as well,
which I think is kind of cool. Looks
very nice. Um, and again, you can do
this. Any of your homies can do this.
>> So, if you put in half
>> Yep. You put in half, your friends can
put in half. Uh, and but whoever I
believe whoever put put it down is the
one who owns it. Have to own it,
>> right? Um, what is also cool about this
is, uh, we also rebalance I'm going to
pull us out of here, too. Rebalance some
building foam stuff. Nothing really
changes here, but there's a more
granularity uh with how this works to
make it a little bit more uh
>> Yeah, this is a good point because
someone did comment earlier on that the
uh the nursery costing 20 foam. They're
like, "What? That's insane." We forgot
to mention uh everything that's actually
like two old foam.
>> Two old foam.
>> New foam that's 20, but old foam that's
just two.
>> Yeah, it is. It is uh it is a
significant difference. And I I think it
might be on the Yeah. Everybody just
look at this slide for a second. Gather
information from it if you need to.
because I'm pretty sure there's another
big one coming in.
>> Also, all these names have changed on
the right.
>> Yeah, it's funny. We put them we so this
slide has the names for this and then I
think two slides later it is a bunch of
the new names for structures.
>> Good.
>> These were all placeholder names
previously. This is what you saw in
cycle 4.
>> Oh, we we have uh if we go back.
>> Yeah.
>> So, uh we
>> that's the same or less. We do have uh
bigger creative aspirations than calling
our uh uh base building assets printer
M.
>> They don't like wall one and wall two. I
can't believe that.
>> Uh ju just to be clear uh people I think
everything cost customer. That's not
true. Uh it's everything is basically
the same price
>> or cheaper.
>> You just get more.
>> Home is just smaller and more of it.
>> Inflation baby.
>> And it says max runs one to three. You
see quantity per run. So it's 30 instead
of one. So you're actually still getting
three times the amount per run. And
correct. Remember those runs are uh
essentially continuous. So as long as
you have the input,
>> every time a printer completes one run,
you will get 30.
>> Yeah.
>> Uh in one go.
>> So what they're saying nicely is Crimea
River.
>> He is trying to say that. Yes. Uh over
here.
>> He's saying we're not being
unreasonable. Really?
>> No, we'll see about that. I'm sure they
will still be Yeah, we'll still have
complaints about it. Uh big news. We did
change the way turrets work because they
were kind of bad before. Uh and not kind
of bad, they were really bad. I think
nobody here is going to disagree with
that. Um they were really hard to
balance and they also were really easily
tricked by
>> Yes.
>> Uh basic strategies. So we're trying to
fix those at least in the short term. Uh
this is a
>> the word smarts was a misnomer. Yeah.
>> Yeah. They were they were not smart,
>> but this is an interim solution.
>> It is an interim solution. It's an
interim solution. uh we have a
longerterm base building uh solution in
mind and that part of that is the uh
destruction and rebuilding that we
talked about fairly recently that's did
not make it in for cycle 5 start uh but
this is a a good um uh a good step in
the right direction at least. So we have
now three new turrets. We have the mini
turret, the turret and the heavy turret.
Uh those uh then are then specializing
in small targets, medium targets and
large targets. Um so those weapons have
those turrets have their own weapons.
you no longer apply weapons to the
turrets. So that way we can balance them
separately. Uh this is probably the best
idea honestly just because it's it just
makes the most sense at least from a in
a short-term point of view. Uh
previously we felt like the paradigm was
really really heavily in favor of the
attackers. I don't think anybody's going
to argue with that. We're now trying to
shift it more towards the defenders so
there's at least uh some balance there
and to make attackers really have to put
in a little bit of effort. Yeah,
>> there exists a theoretical optimal
balance.
>> That optical optimal balance is a
dynamic uh point that always changes.
>> We are in the pursuit of always
following this dynamically changing
theoretical balance point.
>> Yeah.
>> Uh whilst being wrong all the time, but
the pursuit is there no matter if I go
very kind of abstract.
>> Yeah.
>> Uh on it. Uh, also here's another big
one. Uh, initial anchor points for
bases. This is a single lrange point
you're seeing in this image. Uh, we're
adding multiple anchor air. Yeah.
>> Multiple uh base anchor points to all L
points ranging from five to 20 anchors
per location. Players are limited to one
network node per L. But what this does
allow for, at least in the short term,
while we're still working on tribal base
building, is something kind of akin to
tribal base building. You can at least
have
>> neighbors.
>> Neighbors all you and your homies all at
one location. Uh at least at a single L
point. So you can at least see people
nearby.
>> Howdy neighbor.
>> Howdy. Yeah, really is a real howdy
neighbor moment.
>> Go over and like ask to borrow some
sugar.
>> I was going to say,
>> excuse me. Can you spare cup of sugar?
>> Um oh, so here's what we were talking
about earlier. Uh we changed a bunch of
the names of things. I know some people
would get real mad about this because
they don't like things to change, but uh
>> it's still printer M though.
>> It It is still printer M. It that's
true. Well, it's just printer now.
>> Yeah.
>> It lost the M.
>> It undefined.
>> Yeah. So, we're changing just sort of
the I mean, all these names are
placeholder names from previously.
Anyway, uh you know, a hell
>> they're just on the turret. Some people
were asking if uh there's still a
restriction of up to six. Uh my
understanding
>> it's it's on the slide. The next
>> my understanding it's on the next slide.
It is the next. It is the next slide. So
everybody just kind of take a look at
this, observe this information. Uh put
it to your heart. Screenshot it.
>> It is going to be relevant here before
too long. Um and then um actually I
lied. It's not in the next one, but is
in here. Uh no, we uh we removed how
many turrets you can place down at any
given location.
>> It's now just dependent on the power.
The different turrets have different
power requirements.
>> A granted in science thing. It is not.
So if you want to have a network node
just purely surrounded by turrets, you
can do so.
>> You absolutely can build that doom.
>> You have the power for it, you can do
it.
>> The cruelt Yeah.
>> L point just full of losers when they
all get eaten by my turrets.
>> Real uh Okay, here is a big one as well.
And it's so funny because I was talking
to CCP Conr about this just a little bit
ago, uh about how it feels like compared
to what this actually is, there's very
little information up here about it. And
I'm like, this is the biggest page of
text I've got so far. But we are now
rolling out orbital zones, which we were
previously calling landscapes, to every
system in the game. And not only that,
we're also removing all previous
dungeons, all the sites that previously
were resource collection sites, NPC
sites, they are all of them. Every
single one of them are gone. Uh now, if
you want resources in the game, you have
to go into one of the orbital zones. You
have to do a little bit of searching for
it, and all that stuff is out there.
This is coupled with a big distribution
update uh for how resources are
distributed in the universe. Not just
resources, but also NPCs as well. It's
also coupled with uh we are adding 15
new versions of the orbital zones on top
of the original five we had in cycle 4.
They're all unique. They've got new uh
structures, new graphics, new designs,
new volumetrics if you're into volutric
clouds.
Um, we have a uh a huge huge huge huge
huge update to NPCs. Not only are we now
we we we've I don't actually think I
added it here, but there are new NPC
models. We're updating how NPCs interact
with you. They're not only just going to
fly around casually and, you know, look
at things and shoot you if you get
close.
>> They have objectives.
>> They have objectives. They have tasks.
They have goals. They remember. They
think. Uh, and
>> they're like crows.
Don't [ __ ] with Chris. They will move
between points of interest in a star
system, including Yes, they will show up
at your base.
>> Yeah.
>> Yeah. And it's probably worth mentioning
cuz someone uh in chat says, "No more
loot anymore." Wow. And no more ferals
killing and mining sites. And I want to
have the um the Luke Skywalker.
Everything you've just said is wrong
mean because if you read the next line,
it says, "So there is plenty of loot,
trust us." Uh but essentially, there's
like wrecks and objects that are usually
guarded by the NPCs. So, you're no
longer forced to just go farm NPCs for
loot. The NPCs will of course protect
things that they're trying to guard and
stuff like that, but the loot is still
definitely there. And then the NPCs, as
you mentioned, move around, do their own
thing, and if you're in one of the sites
that they like to be around at mining,
then they might come and harass you
>> if you have things that they want.
>> Yes, you can interact as as Proto
Droidbot has found, you can go fullon
like Stardew Valley with the
>> Yeah. Oh, yeah. They'll trade with you.
>> Yeah, they'll trade with you. Yeah.
>> Yeah. They not all of them
>> trade with trade with the crows. Some of
them just
>> some of them will trade weapon fire, but
others are
>> they're exchanging bullets.
>> Yes, they are exchanging bullets. Uh but
yes, we have there. Like I said, this is
this is one page on a slideshow is not
really giving away what all this is.
>> Cer is a huge huge update with a ton of
new visuals. We added we got rid of a
bunch of the old um uh NPC names, the
old um feral uh groups. The termitis,
the Okas, the Sakatas, and the Oza ter
ferals are all gone. They've we've now
introduced new clades of fererals um
that are up to date with the
>> following the lore
>> the lore of the game.
>> Yep. Uh, and in the near future, I was
informed about this by again CCP Con
just a few months ago, uh, the NPCs will
be salvageable and the valuable special
NPCs will have valuable rewards attached
to them. But yes, the NPCs themselves no
longer drop loot. You can get loot from
Rex, you can get loot from D or
information and and resource caches
across the universe, but the NPCs
themselves are really just there to
>> today they're protectors. Yes,
>> I'm sure you will be able to salvage
from them if you can destroy them
gracefully.
>> Yep.
>> I I think worth calling out here with
the um orbital zones.
>> Yeah.
>> And the resources, distributions, etc.
Things are bound to be not perfect in in
the beginning. We're working hard on
making sure especially in the beginning
when you need resources to to progress
to get uh into places you want to live
in in frontier uh we need here community
feedback reporting as much things as
possible that may
>> if you find any place where it's it's
difficult and uh you know that's that
could be because it's difficult but it
could also be because we've made a
mistake.
>> So if you let us know that will be
that'll be very helpful to us. This is
uh also um kind of like the signatures
and scanning thing we talked about
earlier on. This is systemic. Yeah. And
actually gives us a a lot of uh ability
to respond to things quicker without
needing to do like huge patches and
stuff to to address it.
>> Um so we should be able to respond
pretty quickly to these things. But I
mean when a universe is at the moment
25,000 or so solar systems, it can be a
bit hard to test them all.
>> I just had that camera on me looking at
my phone the whole time while you were
talking. It was very strange.
>> Cool.
>> Yeah. No idea. Okay. Moving move ahead.
But can you go sorry back one?
>> Yeah.
>> No, thank you.
>> You're looking at
>> he's reading
>> nothing in the NPC overhaul on NPC yet.
>> It's because he's he's he's too
dangerous to be
>> I find the uh like the file that
controls the intelligence and it was
just blank.
>> You remember he was showing it before
the cloud. It's it's it's constantly
involved.
>> There's a lot of smack talking going on
here. There is I I mean
>> fact stating is what I
>> because they're very small is the thing.
You ever seen a very small dog just go
yap yap yap? That's what's what's
happening inside this desk.
>> Okay.
>> The Okay.
>> Yeah. And there's an Icelandic saying
for it is there.
>> Yeah.
>> Which means
>> uh the
empty barrel has the loudest sound.
>> Sure. Yeah. We've got one in the US too.
It's called talk [ __ ] get hit. Uh, so,
uh,
>> culturally the same,
>> culturally, culturally very similar. Uh,
moving right along, here's a cool video
showing off one of the new, um, uh, the
new, um, landscapes, including a bunch
of signatures over there. You can see
>> or orbital zones, sorry. Thank you,
Orbital Zones. I mean, just look at
that. I think it's so hot.
>> Look at this. Think about the trailer.
>> Yeah. Shout out to the chase camera, of
course, here as well. Being put into
being put into practice. You can see
signatures around the map. You can
actually see this little circular icon
here in the center of the screen or the
circular. Well, you can't it's not
really a circle. There's a circle there
showing you where there are unresolved
signatures around you. Yeah.
>> Uh which is super helpful. Little little
arrows down there. Um and you can't hear
it, but again, whenever there's a new
signature popping up around you, you'll
hear a little tick. It sounds like a
geer counter. Um
and it is super super super uh useful in
these cases. Um, and I think it's pretty
neat. Um, so then I think uh I think
this is I think I have one more of
another. And you can see more of these
over here. Uh, there's more complexity
to some of these. Uh,
>> it's a big signature in the middle
there.
>> A big signature in the middle. Yeah,
it's a really big one.
>> Thick boy.
>> Yeah, real thick real thick lad.
>> That might could it could be something
very valuable.
>> It could be. It could also be a real big
NPC. It could be a a player in a
battleship. on a battleship. It could be
me in a battleship.
>> Um,
>> do signatures say scanned once fully
analyzed? That's the cool thing. No.
Yeah. So, they they degrade. Uh, as your
ship is still in range and receiving
information, you're not going to lose
it. But if you like fly behind a rock,
it's it can track it for a certain
amount of time, but it will lose
resolution to the point that it loses
any information, but signature is gone.
>> Information is only relevant while it's
relevant.
>> Yeah. There's a dead reckoning aspect
like um like a static thing like an
asteroid for example. If you go behind a
rock and come back and there's a
signature in the same place, you would
be able to resolve it quicker because
it's likely it's the same thing. Yeah.
But if it's like a moving NPC and then
you lose track of it and then suddenly
you come out behind a rock and there's
other signatures, it's going to be hard
for it to determine where it is. Again,
>> dead reckoning is a really good way to
look at it. I think uh and if you don't
know what dead reckoning is, Google it.
Uh because it it is informing a lot of
uh I think ideas just sort of general
thought processes for how information is
handled in frontier. Um, we also are
introducing a couple new uh modules. If
you've already seen one of these, you've
seen the uh I can't remember what we
were calling it before. We've introduced
a bunch more now. We've introduced the
hop, skip, and the leap. Um, they are
just the way that you they're basically
the drives make you go real fast. You
get one by default now when you uh start
out. Uh, your starting ship has a skip,
I think is the small one, uh, that goes
onto your wind so you can get through
orbital zones more quickly. You don't
have to build your first one, but you do
have to build ones for bigger ships.
>> Um, and they're all available in the
industry system. Also, here's a big one.
If you haven't read it already, we're
introducing two new types of riffs.
>> Yes,
>> these are micro riffs that are in
basically every system. Uh, micro riffs
can be used to get some amount of crude
out of. It's not always high quality
crude. In fact, it's rarely high quality
food, but it is enough for you to be
able to get get around um even if it's
slowly while you're still looking for
the
>> It's like foraging in the forest and
like picking up like handfuls of
berries. You can keep yourself going,
but it's nothing compared to like
finding like a industrial farm
somewhere.
>> Yeah, exactly. They are like mini rifts.
Uh somebody in chat is already asking.
Uh they are rift.
>> Yeah, marrift. Uh Jesus Christ. Don't
never do that again. You got me doing it
now, too. Uh, and of course we've also
changed up the um uh the starting
regions and move some things around a
little bit to uh try and make it more
make the the beginning of the game more
interesting for more people. Um, here is
what I think is one of the coolest shots
I was able to get all day. Uh, so this
is one of the new micro riffs. Uh, as we
pan around here slow. Oh, there we go.
>> Very.
>> That's the sauce, baby. Look at that.
>> It's very demure.
>> Very demure. Very cute.
>> Mindful. Um I think uh while we watch
this a awesome video,
>> yeah,
>> what we need the founders to help us
with is that these orbital zones are
massive, which is why you have a new
capability now of travel within these
orbital zones.
>> Uh new people coming in won't
necessarily be able to figure it out
immediately. So helping new people
realizing how to travel within these
orbital zones uh explaining also the
signature scanning concept um would be
of great help for us.
>> I mean I found after a little bit of
time uh playing around it became
surprisingly intuitive surprisingly
quickly. I would just open up the the
system map look at uh the different
landscapes knowing what resources I was
looking for. Like I needed um uh water
rice at one point which I came from
comets. So I went out to the far reaches
of the system. Now granted, I do have an
advantage that I work here. However, it
did feel very intuitive very quickly and
I stopped thinking about it actively and
I realized that maybe after half an hour
I wasn't really thinking about it. I was
just doing and it made
>> you're going to want to help the new
players if possible.
>> We are going to have a new tutorial
coming out. Uh which is to say uh
tomorrow I'm working on a new tutorial
which is going to come out on Wednesday.
Uh don't tell uh CPossis that yet. I
think he thinks it's done.
>> Not done.
>> Just tell us.
>> CBossis is done. He would he didn't
watch these streams. She's Bikes does
though. But what Bikes is in California
right now, so he's not watching.
>> He's not watching.
>> What's he going to do?
>> Exactly. Yikes isn't a snitch though.
>> That's true. Um he uh so we are going to
have a new tutorial that'll have a lot
of that information in there for new
players. Um but yes, as always, uh be
good to your fellow man, your fellow
writers. They need as much help as they
remember, you too once were just a
little noob and you needed help as well.
Yeah.
>> Um
>> especially if you were a CP good fellow,
you still need help as much as possible.
Um,
>> don't disagree.
>> We Okay, so here's another big one. If
you are a knower, uh, we are introducing
a bunch of new balance changes to ships.
Um, not only are we introducing a new a
new ship, the lie, which first of all,
shout out to Solinaria, who was the soul
rider who had this one before,
>> he brought the only lie in existence to
the Zerotti event yesterday, which I
think is a charad.
>> I think that's awesome. It was kind of a
big deal, too, because he used the lie
to pull off a bunch of the enforcers at
one point that while so that me and the
uh the malls could go in and just start
blasting at it.
>> It was great until they all started to
ignore him again because they're like,
"Okay, well, we can't catch him. We'll
go back after the the Taties." Then they
just start blasting Tatsies instead. So,
um so in general, we're just making a
bunch of improvements or not
improvements, just changes. Uh up until
this point, the Tats was just kind of
like the the
>> the best the one-stop shop for
everything. It was the best mining ship.
It was the best damage dealing ship. It
was the best everything. Uh, so not only
are we going to probably adjust the
tades to make it slightly worse, we're
also adjusting the frig, the rest of the
frig to make them better. Uh, to
hopefully try and bring these things up
to par with each other and make them
more interesting to fly. Uh, so with
that in mind, uh, here's the first big
change. We're introducing the lie. Here
are some stats over here on the left.
You can read at your own in your own
pace. Um, but basically the lie is kind
of a mix uh between the MCF and the
half. Um, so it it does a little bit of
both. It also is very cool. If you if
you were part of I think cycle one or
two, you remember this as the Microparo.
Uh, this is uh it is a cool little guy.
You can ask Solar about it. He's been
flying it for a couple weeks. Um, and it
is a it's it's fast. It's it's a silver
frigot, but is it's a it's a zippy
little guy. Uh, and it does its job uh
pretty well. Um,
moving on, we made, of course, then some
changes to the Tatis as well. Uh, we've,
uh, reduced or rearranged its slot
layout. We've made it a little bit
faster. Uh, but we've also made its
agility lower. We've changed its angular
speed. Uh, we have, um, uh, also now
removed the ability to put tier 2
engines on destroyers. Uh, to make it a
little bit less, just a little bit less
um, all around.
>> A little less.
>> Yeah, just a little bit less. It should
be good, but it should not be busted and
previously it was
>> busted. Um, moving right along, uh, we
also now have changes to the, um, the
reaver and the recurve. Uh, the recurve,
uh, has been pretty bad compared to the
Reaver for a long time. Uh, so now we're
trying to distinguish it. Uh, make sure
that it has its own identity. Uh, so you
can see we've we've updated it's we've
increased it power grid, made it a
little bit faster. Uh, it is slightly
less agile than it was previously. Um,
and it has a slightly better angular
speed. Uh, the Reaver, for example, has
also had his agility increased and has
had his max angular speed increased as
well. Um, we then we have, of course,
the uh the half and the MCF. Uh, both of
these have been, uh, changed a little
bit as well, just because they weren't
quite fitting in the roles they were
supposed to be fitted into. Um, and we
so the the the HA specifically has um
been improved to become a more combat
focused ship, a a heavy combat focused
ship, while the MCF uh is mostly um had
its mobility adjusted. Uh which I think
these two I I flew the half a little bit
earlier.
It feels like a heavy frig. I'll give
you that. And it feels strong um in a
way that it maybe didn't before. Um,
and then of course we have the three uh
the Let's go back here real fast. Come
on.
There we go. Uh, the three biggest ships
in the game, the Maul, the Lore, and the
Chumach have all been adjusted slightly.
The Maul has had its uh slot profiles
adjusted as well. It also adds an
additional high slot that supports
turrets. So, the Maul is just better uh
now than it was before. And the Laura
and Schumach also are just have their
mass adjusted a little bit. Uh the Laura
is slightly larger and the Chumaka is
slightly smaller.
>> And remember that that mass is now
important because you are now more
detectable.
>> Yep. Yes, you are the Yeah. If you are
in a bigger ship, you are more easily
visible uh to other players in the
universe. Um so we've also changed up
the ninetic armor weave, the adaptive
nitic armor weave rather. Um we also
added to the market, the weave 4. Please
stop messaging me about it. Uh I I weep
now.
>> We need to test that it works. So every
time you find her on the market, please
message this.
>> You should she should not do that.
>> Data point important.
>> I'm begging you. Please let me rest. Uh
we so we did do this some notes here as
well for that if you want to know more
about it. Uh we had a bunch of audio
updates that are very cool. Shout out to
CCP
>> rolls. Rolls.
>> No, he's not rolls anymore. He's
changing
>> CCP uh audio.
>> Heretic. That's right. CP heretic. I
like that.
>> Yeah, it's good.
>> That's a good one.
>> Uh CP Heretic who went through and added
a bunch of really cool new sounds.
You'll notice immediately I think the
very first like your spawn in has new
music, new battle music too, which is
super super cool.
>> A lot of new uh sound effects as well
for weapons also.
>> Um and then for art updates, uh shout
out to the art team who is always kind
of ky about what information they have
available. Uh here's some stuff and I'm
going to show you some images. Just know
that it's a lot. Everything that has
been touched previously up to this point
has had art passes done to it. Um
there's a lot of stuff in here. Um
>> and I want to I want to call out that
you know over the next two weeks that
that same art team continues to iterate.
>> So we're going to see even more coming
out
>> indeed. Uh okay, let's go ahead and then
look at this is another rift. Uh you can
see this a cool red energy. Um I don't
know which rift this was, but it is a
rift. Uh certainly
>> can't confirm.
>> Can't confirm. It's very rift. I think
this is the red one.
>> This is the red one.
>> The other one conversely known as the
blue one
>> blue one. Yeah. Yeah. Uh we have uh some
cool images here of uh some of the uh
new orbital zones. Some cool uh stuff
going on in these. Uh and then we have
new turret models. Uh this is not I
think for every single weapon, but a lot
of the weapons have new turret models.
>> Yeah. The cool thing is these are all
dynamic models that move around, do
stuff, have VFX attached to them.
They're not just like static
>> bits of geometry. They're actually
pretty
>> turrets. Yeah.
>> Yeah. They look very cool in action.
>> There are a couple of them that I wanted
to include in here, but I think there's
a bug in them on a couple of them right
now where So, right now you can see
these the axes show as 21 meters long.
So, it it scales the frame of that image
at 21 meters. Some of them have an axis
that's like 800 meters long. So, when
you go to pull up the images of them,
they're tiny in the center. You can't
see anything.
>> A problem for another day. Uh so, a lot
of cool new uh turret models in here as
well.
>> Looking [ __ ] cool.
>> Weapon, weapon, VFX, everything. It's
all great. Uh so here's the end of it.
Uh the cycle 5 starts on March 11th.
That is Wednesday. The downtime will
begin at 900 a.m. UTC. That is 5:00 a.m.
Eastern. Uh and uh what is it like
>> 1?
>> No, it's day savings is over 2 am I
think
>> Pacific now.
>> That's right.
>> Um this is a pretty big technical lift
obviously.
>> I like that increased technical lift. we
just, you know, entirely change the
entire tax stack. This is
>> it is it is going to probably cause uh a
is it's a big one. We're expecting it to
last, I think, maybe 7 hours is what
we're aiming for.
>> Take us our day to do it.
>> Yeah.
>> And we'll get it up as soon as we can.
>> Indeed. Uh so we hoping to end downtime
around 4:00 uh UTC, 4 o'clock in the
afternoon. Uh, of course stay tuned in
Discord and we will let you know if
anything changes.
>> I mean, so
>> we should have like a full TV of just
you watching.
>> We had actually talked about we got to
go live. We have talked about something
similar to that. I will say like this is
the number of people involved in doing
the press button get new version of e
printier will be quite significant. The
biggest uh group of people that need to
all do stuff at the same time and all
the stuff needs to connect and link.
Yeah,
>> it is a a pretty substantial effort.
There's in the region of like 20 plus
people who are going to be doing stuff
that all has to happen at the same time,
which is why we're giving ourselves
plenty of time to do this practicing it
now and getting it wrong now, but we're
going to be better by then.
>> So, I have given us um what I think is
uh hopefully touchwood a suitable amount
of time to get this all done in a nice
slow relaxed manner. To that end, I have
booked a cake for 300 p.m. UTC.
>> Oh, no. So, I am putting my my cake
where my mouth is in this instance.
>> Hopefully you
>> for me. Hopefully.
>> Um, so the team cake. Uh, so I'm hoping
that for you
it's just for me.
>> You guys You guys did a great job.
>> Roll a giant shaker
overload.
>> Good job overload. Yeah. Hey.
>> Uh, so I'm hoping that uh things will be
in a nice good state. That'll give us
plenty of time to just jump on test
stuff and then we if it is ready in
advance, we're not going to open it
early. It's not fair for those of you
who are like, you know, aiming for that
time. So, it will be no earlier than
1600, but hopefully um that is more than
enough time and then we'll know for the
future.
>> Someone in chat want to know when cycle
five starts.
>> We'll never know.
>> It's there. That's the the one. That's
cycle five.
>> Do you have is it the last slide?
I think also worth calling out as you
mentioned on Friday uh this is uh big
neck and lift as you see it all there's
a lot of things that the entire game
play experience of Frontier is changing
with this release period I'm not trying
to overhype it I think it's just like
more of a
>> No it's true fact
>> it is
>> yeah u we recognize that we know this
will be a bit chaotic like we operate on
that assumption if we somehow got it all
right perfect uh I Um, the odds are
against us. Um, so we need the font
playing.
>> Yeah. 30,000 files getting changed. I'm
sure we didn't mess up anything in any
of those files.
>> Exactly. Uh, uh, we know that is the
case. We're prepping for that. So, the
next two to three weeks are us playing
the game uh, and iterating on the live
experience with the founders. So, we
need everybody playing. We need
everybody commenting on Discord. We'll
be aggressively going through it all. We
need everybody talking in um chat
channels uh giving us feedback inside
the game. We need people filing bug
reports um etc etc. Uh play play give us
feedback and we will you will see the
experience improve right in front of
your eyes.
>> We'll be fixing things continually.
>> Yeah,
>> exactly.
>> Uh we are going to be doing another
stream on Wednesday. We have three
streams this week. Uh we'll do a stream
on Wednesday to kick off the hackathon.
I don't know who's actually going to be
on that stream because I'm pretty sure
everybody who needs to be involved is
going to be working
>> deploying
>> during the deployment. So,
>> I can join.
>> Yeah,
>> I will show my work.
>> I've got you down for critical uh roles
on that day.
>> Eat the cake.
>> Got to eat the cake.
>> Someone's going to eat the cake. Uh
>> you've been assigned at least 50% of the
cake. We're going to bring some of the
cake in here.
>> Yeah, we'll just we'll just eat cake.
>> I'll eat the cake here.
>> That'll be our kickoff stream. We'll
just eat cake.
>> When's the kickoff stream?
>> I have not given I've not I don't have a
time yet.
>> Well, I'll tell you one thing. If you
want cake, it has to be after 3 p.m.
>> Very good.
>> Let's have a cake stream. I'll leave a
cake. Sure, we can do a cake stream.
>> We can do the couch stream. We talked
about
>> We are going to do So, here's what we're
going to do. Uh, also on Friday, we're
going to be doing a let's play of Cycle
5.
>> Nice.
>> Live from our studio or the studio live
from the office here. You'll be seeing
me playing the game. We'll have a couch
set up. You'll see the whole office just
kind of me mingling back there. Uh,
you'll have people sitting at the at the
couch watching. I have a big monitor.
They can just sort of watch the Are
>> No, we're gonna heckle.
>> Yeah,
>> I was gonna pretend I was asking for
permission.
>> It was permission granted.
>> Uh, so we're going to be doing that. If
you want to watch that stream, that'll
be I think we'll take over Frontier
Friday this next week.
>> Um, maybe I'll try and see if I can bump
off uh uh live to feed so we can go a
little bit longer.
>> Live to feed thing. join the have the
online community team to be honest.
>> Yeah, we'll see. We'll see. They're a
little dodgy. Those those community team
guys, you can't trust them. Uh uh that
being said, except for CB Convict, who
is a real homie today. Thank you, CB
Convict and CB and Zealous, who's my
number one day. And CB Okay, they're all
great. They're all good.
>> They're all good. Um
>> yes,
>> that all being said, uh that's all we've
got for now. We're going to have the
patch notes that will go out on
Wednesday morning. Um
>> why do we just put them out? put out
today.
>> We could. I mean, we've just told
everyone.
>> Let me make sure they're done. Let me
make sure that everybody, all the devs
have finished all this. I'm going to, in
fact, when we're finished here,
>> do a dead check.
>> I'm going to walk over to the office and
I'm going to say, "Hey, this is the
absolute last call because when I go
home, I'm going to publish the patch
notes. You need to get it done.
>> I think we'll have everything. So,
>> but this is more a testament of
everything that has gone in. We aren't
sure if this is capturing everything."
Yeah. Um, yeah,
>> there's a lot.
>> There's a lot. Uh, so we'll have
patchments coming out here soon. Uh
we'll have more information about the
launch on Wednesday when we have uh when
we actually go down. We'll keep you guys
updated about all new uh things. If you
haven't yet, go check out the trailer
for Cycle 5. It's super cool. You can
see CB Goodfellow yapping uh which you
should be used to at this point.
Honestly,
>> I recommended someone in Discord start
some sort of sweep stake at how many
minutes after 9:00 a.m. we get the first
person asking why the server's offline.
It happens every time.
>> It's it's inevitable. Um so yeah, that's
it. Uh, thank you so much for joining us
here on Frontier Monday. Uh, which is
very unusual. Uh, but we we love doing
these.
>> Yeah, we love Mondays.
>> Yeah, big fan of Mondays. Uh, I've been
CB. This has been CB.
>> That's been CB Good Fella and that's
been CB overload. Thank you all so much.
We'll see you on Wednesday for the start
of cycle 5. And until next time, my
friends,
>> we'll see you on the frontier.
>> Have a good day.